<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The ornament of women. Or, A description of the true excellency of women Delivered in a sermon at the funerall of M. Elizabeth Machell, on Easter Munday being the 15. of April 1639. By Stephen Geree, minister of Gods Word at Wonnersh, neare Guildford in Surrey.</title>
            <author>Geree, Stephen, 1594-1656?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01632</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11763</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118756</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853963</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853963</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19368</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01632)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19368)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1066:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The ornament of women. Or, A description of the true excellency of women Delivered in a sermon at the funerall of M. Elizabeth Machell, on Easter Munday being the 15. of April 1639. By Stephen Geree, minister of Gods Word at Wonnersh, neare Guildford in Surrey.</title>
                  <author>Geree, Stephen, 1594-1656?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[34], 95, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. B[adger] for L. F[awne] and S. G[ellibrand] and are to be sold at the signe of the Brazen Serpent, in Pauls Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1639.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's and publishers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Machell, Elizabeth, d. 1639.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19368:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19368:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ORNAMENT <hi>of</hi> WOMEN. <hi>OR,</hi> A deſcription of the true excellency of <hi>Women.</hi> Delivered in a Sermon at the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of M. ELIZABETH MACHELL, on <hi>Eaſter</hi> Munday being the 15. of <hi>April</hi> 1639. By <hi>Stephen Geree,</hi> MINISTER of <hi>Gods</hi> Word at <hi>Wonnerſh,</hi> neare <hi>Guildford</hi> in SURREY.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. 12.4.</hi>
               </bibl> A vertuous woman is a Crowne to her Husband.</q>
            <q>Proijciamus ornamenta terrena ſi caelestia optamus <bibl>
                  <hi>Tertul.</hi> de Cult. Foemin.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. B.</hi> for <hi>L. F.</hi> and <hi>S. G.</hi> and are to be ſold at the Signe of the Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen Serpent, in Pauls Church-Yard 1639.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19368:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19368:2"/>
            <head>TO the Right Honourable, <hi>Gerard</hi> LORD <hi>Angier</hi> Baron of LONGFORD all true Honour and happines both in this life, and that which is to come.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honour:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was a tart and yet true cenſure of the Popes Clergie,
<note place="margin">Bonifac. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſc. <hi>In Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burenſi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil: Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do Sacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes habui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus aureos, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> vaſis lig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neis uteba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, nuno eum ligneos ſacerdotes habemus, aureis va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis utuntur</hi>
               </note>
               <pb facs="tcp:19368:3"/>
               <hi>That they had golden Chali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but wooden Prieſts.</hi> The like may not unfitly bee affirmed of ſome women, who <hi>have golden garments, and guilded bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, but wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, or leaden ſoules.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ber. Epiſt. 113.</note> For as <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi> Bernhard ſaid of
<pb facs="tcp:19368:3"/>ſome. <hi>Induuntur purpura &amp; byſſo, &amp; ſubinde conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia pannoſa ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet.</hi> They are clad with Purple and ſilke, but the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the meane while lies torne and tattered. <hi>Fulgent monilibus; ſed ſordent moribus,</hi> (ſaith the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour)
<pb facs="tcp:19368:4"/>
               <hi>they ſhine and make a brave ſhew with brace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets and Iewels, but are baſe and ſordid in their maners and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it was farre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>otherwiſe with your Honours <hi>worthy kinſwoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whoſe adorning was not
<pb facs="tcp:19368:4"/>outward in wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of gold, or putting on of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell,
<note place="margin">1 Peter 3.3, 4.</note> but the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament of a meek and quiet ſpirit, which is much ſet by in the ſight of God.</hi> Therefore I have the rather preſumed to prefixe your Noble name to this diſcourſe of
<pb facs="tcp:19368:5"/>mine (how meane ſoever) hoping of Your Honours ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, in regard of the relation that it hath to that most worthy, &amp; (in mine opinion) matchleſse Gentlewoman, of whoſe rare vertues, and ſingular graces Your Lordſhip hath often beene an eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:19368:5"/>and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer. So that I am aſſured you will thinke it no preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to Your High and profound ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to caſt your eyes upon ſuch an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly body, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limated ſoule, as ſhe was, but rather ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it as a meanes to refine Your deepe
<pb facs="tcp:19368:6"/>contemplations, and make them aſcend above the <hi>Stars</hi> and al <hi>inferiour Orbs</hi> even into the <hi>third Heaven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.2, 4. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> where the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> heard un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable words, which is not poſsible for man to utter, which all <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Sciences</hi> are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of, ſave that
<pb facs="tcp:19368:6"/>which is called <hi>Ars artium, &amp; Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia ſcientiarum,</hi> to wit, <hi>Divinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For this bleſſed <hi>Gentlwoman</hi> was the <hi>mirrour</hi> of her time, conſidering her <hi>Age,</hi> and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentage,</hi> and may bee a <hi>Patterne</hi> to Poſterity, both for admiration, and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation,
<pb facs="tcp:19368:7"/>Becauſe ſhe ſo ſeriouſly bent her beſt indeavours to the beſt things. For having once found that <hi>Pearle of greateſt price,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. ver. 45, 46.</note> ſhe was willing with the wiſe <hi>Merchant</hi> to part with all for the purchaſe of it, as being the <hi>only or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament</hi> of men and women, ſurmoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="tcp:19368:7"/>al other pearls and precious ſtones. She was able <hi>to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne of thing; that differ, and did approve the things that are excellent,</hi> ſo that ſhe became, <hi>wiſer than the ancient, becauſe ſhee kept GODS precepts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 119.100.</note> wherby ſhe was ripe
<pb facs="tcp:19368:8"/>for heaven, before others of her age, and quality, begin ſo much as ſeriouſly to ſet themſelves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that holy place. She could not ſatisfie her ſelfe, as moſt doe, with that which went for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in <hi>Salvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> time,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Genus quod <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis, minus eſſe vitioſu.</hi> Salv. <hi>De Guber.</hi> lib. 3. pag. 88.</note> when it was counted <hi>ſome
<pb facs="tcp:19368:8"/>kind of Sanctitie to bee leſſe ſinfull than others.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.13, 14.</note> But <hi>forgetting that which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde, and reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out to that, which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſhee preſſed toward the mark, for the high cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of GOD in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19368:9"/>
            <p>Therefore I had two ſpeciall motives which induced mee to wenter this little labour into the light in this <hi>curious,</hi> and <hi>criticall</hi> age.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> To preſerve the happie memory of Your Lordſhips deare and well-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving Neece, who was <hi>worthie
<pb facs="tcp:19368:9"/>to be had in ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <note place="margin">Your zeale hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked very many, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.2.</note> That by her zealous and Heavenly Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple J might (if it were poſsible) wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and quicken the dead, and drouzie hearts of men and women, who in the worſt things want
<pb facs="tcp:19368:10"/>the bridle, but in the beſt the ſpurre. J know that the beſt men or women, want warmth and heate in this old, and cold age of the world, therefore I thought ſo lively, and ſpark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a ſpirit as ſhee had, might bee of much force to make many, either bluſh
<pb facs="tcp:19368:10"/>for ſhame, or burne with zeale for the glory of God.</p>
            <p>Thus Noble Lord having had often experience of Your rare humility and courteſie, as alſo of your approved piety and charity; I was willing by theſe lines to let the world know, how much J
<pb facs="tcp:19368:11"/>honor you, and your choyce learning, mixt with ſingular modeſty, and inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity, which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed true Nobility But being perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that you had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do things praiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy than read your own praiſes,
<note place="margin">Facere lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danda qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> audire lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>data malu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſes.</note> I. reſt, and humbly take leave, with all
<pb facs="tcp:19368:11"/>due reſpect and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to your Noble ſelfe, and much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured <hi>Lady,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty to drop downe his beſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon you both.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours to be commanded in</hi> Chriſt Ieſus. <hi>STEPH: GEREE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19368:12"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19368:12"/>
            <head>TO The truly Noble and Pious SISTERS Miſt. <hi>Elizabeth Machell,</hi> and the LADY <hi>Letice Holcrofte,</hi> Grace and Peace be multiplied.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Much Honoured,</hi> &amp;c.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Make bold to joyn you both in this Epiſtle, whom GOD hath lincked with thoſe firm bonds of Nature, Affection, and eſpecially true Religion, which is <hi>a threefold Cord not eaſily broken.</hi> I know you both would be heartily glad to ſee her Picture, for whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:19368:13"/>ſake I have ſet Pen to paper at this preſent. But I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, that no Limner could draw her to the life, becauſe <hi>ſhe was all glorious within,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.13.</note> 
               <hi>and her life hid with Chriſt in God, Col.</hi> 3.3.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſeeing ſhe muſt bee repreſented rather by a <hi>Penne</hi> than a <hi>Penſil,</hi> I have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to ſet before your eyes ſuch a rude draught, as my preſent, and urgent occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions would ſuffer me to make at her <hi>Funerall.</hi> And becauſe thoſe Peeces pleaſe the judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious beſt, which are rather true than rich, or gaudy, I have ſtudyed to ſet her forth in her owne proper colours, not with gariſh Eloquence, and gaudy words, but in that language, which ſhee beſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.</p>
            <p>Now that I may ſpeake a
<pb facs="tcp:19368:13"/>word in ſeaſon to you in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall. Firſt, for you her deare Mother, in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of all your mourning let this ſolace your ſoule and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that you were not onely the Mother of ſuch a daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but had an hand in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king her <hi>a daughter of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, yea of Almighty God.</hi> Your good inſtructions, and example, in frequenting the houſe of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were a maine motive, (no doubt) to make her in love with that good Word of GOD, which wrought ſo effectually, and in a manner miraculouſly in her, therfore you have much more cauſe of joy and gladneſſe, than of griefe and heavineſſe. If all Parents would but give ſuch example as you have done, both at home and in Gods houſe, ô what holy and
<pb facs="tcp:19368:14"/>happy houſes, and congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhould we have! what thronging and crowding would there bee in moſt Churches, which now are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt empty oftentimes! But when moſt Parents provide rather for their Childrens bodies than ſoules, making much of the Carkas, neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Conſcience, no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile that there is ſo little hope in moſt of their Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</p>
            <p>Goe on therfore with good ſucceſſe as you have begun, and ſtill doe more and more worthily in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> GOD hath given you an heart, not only to be a <hi>Favourer,</hi> which is eaſie, but a <hi>Follower,</hi> yea, and a <hi>Furtherer</hi> of thoſe that hee hath ſent into his Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard: the ſame Lord multiply his mercy, grace and ſpirit
<pb facs="tcp:19368:14"/>upon you and yours, that you may ſtill prove Noble pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes unto others.</p>
            <p>And now good Madam, to returne to your Ladiſhip, I know you bare no ſmall ſhare of ſorrow with your beloved Siſter in this buſineſſe, becauſe you have a long time loved your deceaſed Kinſwoman, as if ſhee had beene your owne daughter: witneſſe thoſe affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate words of ſalutation, which you uſually inſerted into the Letters your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſent to her Mother, which ever had a ſpeciall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and emphaſis, when you came to her. Inſomuch as I dare boldly ſay, you deſire no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more to your deareſt daughters than ſuch a dowry of grace and goodneſſe as her heavenly Father had beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on her.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19368:15"/>
            <p>For you knew her farre dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from the diſpoſition of other Gentlewomen, who make their ſoules ſlaves to their bodyes, and both ſoule and body, drudges to the world and the Devill, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, whereas other <hi>women trouble themſelves with many things like Martha, ſhee ſet her ſoule upon that one thing neceſſary, chuſing with Mary that better part, which could not be taken from her, Luk.</hi> 10. laſt ver.</p>
            <p>Shee was never more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent than when ſhee was to deale with GOD in his holy Ordinances, and in nothing ſo negligent, as in the world, and things of the world, and yet ſhee complained on her death bed, that ſhe had beene too worldly, Alas! what cauſe then have wee to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine
<pb facs="tcp:19368:15"/>of others, who dote ſo much upon the droſſe and dung of the world, and make it no better than an Idoll!</p>
            <p>That precious time which other Gentlevvomen vvick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly waſt in tricking and trimming the body, ſhe ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſpent in decking and adorning the ſoule, for vvhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever was to bee done, the ſoule ſhould not be forgotten. And vvhereas others are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up with faire buildings and ſtately houſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhee mainely minded to beautifie her houſe, not only vvith <hi>the Forme of godlineſſe,</hi> vvhich many families have,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.4.</note> but moſt of all with the <hi>Power of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe,</hi> vvhich few regard. And hence vvas it that ſhe ſo much deſired to have the <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall care of Families</hi> commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded unto others at her Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.
<pb facs="tcp:19368:16"/>For ſhe ſet up her reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution with worthy <hi>Ioſhuah.</hi> Let others doe what they would,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 24.15.</note> 
               <hi>follow the world, or ſerve their luſts, and the times. She and her houſe would ſerve the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither was ſhee afraid to owne Chriſt as many are, who think it more generous; to ſet up ſports and paſtimes, and follow pleaſures <hi>&amp;c.</hi> than ſet up Chriſt and his ordinances in their houſes.</p>
            <p>Moreover her <hi>charity</hi> did notably ſecond her <hi>Piety,</hi> for not only the <hi>loynes of the poore but their bellyes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 31.20. Shee was willing to heale their ſores, and helpe their ſouls giving them good inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as well as plaſters.</note> 
               <hi>and backes did bleſſe her,</hi> as <hi>Job</hi> ſpeakes, yea, their legges and hands, their eyes and cares, did pronounce her bleſſed. So that we have great <hi>cauſe to give God thanks for her work of faith, and labour of love, as the Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaks,
<pb facs="tcp:19368:16"/>1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.3. There be ſome, that have Piety, but want Charity, ſuch are but as ſounding braſſe and tinckling Cymbals, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.1. And ſome againe have a kinde of Charity; but care not for Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, <hi>they give much Almes, but doe not give themſelves to God, nor give over their ſinnes.</hi> Such Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Multi ſunt qui faciunt eleemoſyna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; tamen peccare non ceſsant tiſti quaſi ſua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> offerunt Deo &amp; ſeip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſos Diabolo.</hi> Amb. Ser. 12.</note> 
               <hi>give their goods to God, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the devill.</hi> But your worthy Kinſwoman was none ſuch, for <hi>first ſhe gave her ſelfe to God as the Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donians did, and then to Gods Meſſengers, and to the Saints,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</p>
            <p>What then though ſhee dyed a diſtaſtfull death by reaſon of her diſeaſe? Yet ſhe left a moſt ſweet ſmell and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour behinde her, even the precious oyntment of a good
<pb facs="tcp:19368:17"/>Name, ſo that the day of her death was much better than the day of her birth, as <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſaith, in the ſame place, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.1. Whereas many others, that die of faire diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſes leave a noyſome and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſavoury ſent behinde them, going out like the ſnuffe of a Candle.</p>
            <p>This was that which made her ſo ready to reſigne her will to Gods in greateſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities, and towards her latter end, ſo much to long <hi>to goe home</hi> (as her words were) for ſhee made no more of death than a departing home, ſo that we ſaw her ſomething troubled, when thoſe that were about her laboured to preſerve her life, ſaying, <hi>Why will you not let me goe?</hi> as if they did hinder her happines. Thus with my ſingular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb facs="tcp:19368:17"/>to you both, and thoſe that bee moſt neare unto you, commending you, and all yours to the grace of our God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.20.</note> 
               <hi>who is able to doe excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding abundantly above all wee can aske or thinke,</hi> I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours much obliged <hi>Stephen Geree.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:19368:18"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19368:18"/>
            <head>THE ORNAMENT of <hi>Women.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PRO. 31.29, 30.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Many daughters have done vertuouſly, but thou excelleſt them all.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>VER. 30.</hi>
                     </bibl> Favour is deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and beauty is vaine, but a Woman that feareth the Lord ſhe ſhall be praiſed.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His laſt Chapter of the <hi>Proverbs,</hi> containes cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſingular leſſons, which <hi>Lemuel,</hi> or <hi>Solomon,</hi> learn't of his lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19368:19"/>and religious mother <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> as is gathered from the firſt and ſecond verſes.</p>
            <p>Whereby we may juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confute the folly or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther blaſphemy of thoſe, <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> that cannot endure Women ſhould meddle with the Scriptures or Word of God. For if the words of a Woman were thought fit to bee made the word of God, not only by wiſe <hi>Solomon;</hi> but alſo by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> then ſurely Women may very well meddle with Gods holy word, that following this holy and royall example
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19368:19"/>of <hi>Solomons</hi> Mother, they may inſtruct, at leaſt, their child: <hi>in the old good way</hi> according to GODS Word.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 6.16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The truth is, many wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men doe ſhame a great many men, that are <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, idle, or prophane,</hi> and hence they ſeeke to fright them from the Word of God, that they might be as bad as them, or that themſelves might not ſeeme ſo bad as they be.</p>
            <p>In the body of this Chap. we find two maine things conſiderable, the
<list>
                  <item>1. Concerning Man, the</item>
                  <item>2. Concerning Woman.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt, declares how a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19368:20"/>
               <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>great man</hi> may, and ought to bee, a <hi>good man,</hi> from the beginning of the third unto the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſhewes the <hi>praiſes</hi> and properties of a <hi>great and good woman</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially. Her <hi>praiſes</hi> are ſet downe firſt and laſt, her <hi>properties</hi> are in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt. Wherein wee may ſee her behaviour.</p>
            <p>Firſt, As ſhe is a <hi>Wife, ver.</hi> 11.12.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of a good wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</note> As a <hi>Mother</hi> and <hi>Miſtreſſe</hi> of a <hi>Family,</hi> verſe 13.14. &amp;c. to 28. In all which wee may take notice of her ſingular <hi>faithfulneſſe</hi> and <hi>helpeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:19368:20"/>her <hi>painefulneſſe</hi> and <hi>providence,</hi> her <hi>prudence</hi> and <hi>watchfulneſſe,</hi> and that which ſeaſons all her <hi>Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> Rare ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues in a man, much more in a woman, who is the <hi>weaker veſſell.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. Her praiſes</note>
            </p>
            <p>As for her <hi>praiſe</hi> (to come more punctually to that, becauſe the Text is a part of it) we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider. Firſt, Her <hi>rareneſſe,</hi> hard to be found, intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the interrogation. Who can finde a vertuous woman? That is, they are <hi>rare birds,</hi> and even almoſt <hi>blacke Swannes,</hi> not every where nor eaſie to bee found. Secondly, Her <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparableneſſe,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19368:21"/>her price is farre above Rubyes</hi> or the moſt precious Stones. <hi>Ibid:</hi> not only above, but farre above Rubies. So much for her praiſe in the firſt place. In the ſecond you ſhall finde</p>
            <p>Firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>Of whom</hi> ſhee is praiſed, namely thoſe that beſt knew her, to wit, her husband and child: <hi>Her children ariſe up and call her bleſſed, her husband alſo, and he praiſeth her, ver.</hi> 28.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The <hi>quality</hi> of her praiſe,
<note place="margin">Ver. 29. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> which is ſet downe firſt to be <hi>ſuperla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> farre ſurmounting all other in the firſt verſe of the Text. <hi>Many daughters
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19368:21"/>have done vertuouſly; but thou excelleſt,</hi> or <hi>goeſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond, and above them all,</hi> as the Hebrew hath it.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">Ver. 30.</note> 
               <hi>Compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> in the latter verſe, <hi>Favour is deceitfull and beauty is vaine, or vanity it ſelfe: but a woman that feareth the Lord ſhe ſhall be praiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> take notice of that for which this good woman is chiefly praiſed,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> v. 30</note> to wit, for her <hi>feare of God,</hi> that is for her <hi>grace, true Religion,</hi> and <hi>piety</hi> towards God.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The <hi>place</hi> where ſhe ſhould be praiſed,
<note place="margin">Ver. 31</note> even in the <hi>Gate,</hi> that is in the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19368:22"/>moſt publike place of concourſe and meeting, for in the Gates were there publike meetings and aſſemblies, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards or puniſhments.</p>
            <p>And here it is to bee obſerved,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Continet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieris alpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betico ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne exara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum. Iun.</hi> Ibid.</note> that all this is ſet downe in an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary order, even <hi>Alpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betically</hi> in the <hi>Originall,</hi> both according to the <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> and <hi>number</hi> of the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew Letters,</hi> there being juſt ſo many verſes as let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, to wit, twenty two concerning this <hi>great</hi> and <hi>good woman.</hi> Which is ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome uſed in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: and alwayes upon ſpeciall occaſion, to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19368:22"/>the <hi>choiceneſſe</hi> of the matter in hand, and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them the rather to read, and learne thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect leſſons.</p>
            <p>In the Text then wee have the praiſe of a <hi>Wife</hi> or <hi>Woman in print,</hi> (as I may ſay) a woman farre more worth than her waight in gold: whence the firſt and maine point, that I will obſerve ſhall be this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Grace and godlineſſe are the moſt excellent Ornaments of Women.</hi> Or thus, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>The feare of God and true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion make moſt excellent wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and wives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is as much diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19368:23"/>betweene a gracious Woman and one that wants grace and true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
<note place="margin">Yee were ſometime darkeneſſe but now light in the Lord. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Vide.</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.5.</note> as betweene the light of the Sunne and the light of the Moone and leſſer Starres. While the Sunne is out of ſight, the Moone makes a faire ſhow, and the leſſer ſtars doe ſhine, alſo till the Sun begin to ſhow himſelfe in the <hi>Horizon,</hi> then the Moone doth as it were loſe all her light, looking wan and pale, and the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe ſtarres vaniſh, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare not at all:
<note place="margin">Rotten wood will ſhine in the night in the darke.</note> So a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that wants grace may make great ſhow in the night amongſt the leſſer
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19368:23"/>ſtarres, and ſeeme glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſhee may exceed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and ſhine much in wealth, and beauty, and comlines, yea and in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall vertues, as diſcretion and diligence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which make a faire ſhow in the world,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.19.</note> 
               <hi>that lies in wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and ſo in darkeneſſe; but when a true religious woman comes in place, that is adorned with the feare of God and the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Gods Spirit, then the other is quite obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and darkened, in the eyes of thoſe that can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne of things that dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer. And that which is here ſpoken of women,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19368:24"/>you may likewiſe all along apply unto men. For grace and GODS feare make as great a difference among men as amongſt women.</p>
            <p>Hence <hi>David</hi> cals the <hi>Saints the excellent of the earth, in whom was all his delight, Pſalm.</hi> 16.3. And wiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> his ſonne ſaith. <hi>The righteous is more excellent than his neighbour Prov.</hi> 12.26. for he found by experience, (who tried more than any man) that all was vanity, yea vanity of vanities, that is ſuperla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively vaine without <hi>the feare of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The main thing that makes a man.</note> 
               <hi>and keeping his Commandements;</hi> which,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19368:24"/>he ſaid, was <hi>Col haadam; the whole man,</hi> or <hi>the whole duty of man, Eccleſ.</hi> 12.13.</p>
            <p>This will eaſily appeare to a ſpirituall eye,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Omnis ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo. Arias Mont. Totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Homints Jun.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Sep.</note> that grace and the feare of <hi>God</hi> makes the moſt excellent women and wives, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuch as bee truely gracious excell all others in all thoſe things that are moſt commended in a woman.</p>
            <p>As firſt to begin with their <hi>Birth.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
            </p>
            <p>It is greatly eſteemed in man or woman to bee nobly borne,
<note place="margin">The graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man doth excell in Birth.</note> and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably deſcended, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny make a great ſhew, and carry themſelves high, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19368:25"/>of their great birth, and it breeds eſtimation in others. But now every gracious woman exceeds in her <hi>birth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.3. &amp; 1. and 13.</note> becauſe <hi>borne from above,</hi> even borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new of God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt nobly borne, yea moſt royally deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: It is a great matter to be mans <hi>firſt borne,</hi> and therefore the firſt borne was called <hi>the excellency of dignity, and the excellency of power,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.22. <hi>Jſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> is my ſonne even my firſt borne.</note> 
               <hi>Gen</hi> 49.3. Now all thoſe that feare God aright, and have true grace, are <hi>Gods first borne,</hi> both men and women, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.23. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are the excellency of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19368:25"/>Gods dignity, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of his power, who is omnipotent, even El-ſhaddai all-ſufficient, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1.</p>
            <p>Next to <hi>birth</hi> that which commends a woman is <hi>Beauty,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Beauty.</note> wherewith men are much taken, and even bewitched as it were, ſometimes to the loſſe of their wits and lives alſo, if they cannot obtaine. Now there is no beauty to the <hi>beauty of holineſſe,</hi> which is the bleſſed <hi>Image of God, Epheſ.</hi> 4.24. and makes us like our Lord and Saviour, <hi>who is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lovelie, Cant.</hi> 5.16. All other beauty is but
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19368:26"/>blackneſſe to this, which is the true beauty of every <hi>gracious woman fearing God,</hi> and which ſhe moſt of all prizeth, and ſeekes after.</p>
            <p>The next thing that commends a woman is <hi>favour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. Favour.</note> to be well favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red is amiable in the eyes of men, yet the text here will tell you, that as <hi>Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is vaine, ſo favour is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull,</hi> being compared with <hi>the feare of God.</hi> For the feare of the Lord makes us well favoured in the ſight of God: this is that therefore which makes men or women ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell all others who are
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19368:26"/>fouly deformed, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſinne and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Theſe are chiefe things that make a woman praiſe-worthy in regard of the body. Wherein you ſee <hi>Religion and the feare of God</hi> hath gotten the preheminence.</p>
            <p>Now for the things that commend the ſoule,
<note place="margin">The godly woman ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels in the inward qualities, as firſt in her judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</note> we ſhall ſee the ſame dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference. As firſt for <hi>Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and underſtanding,</hi> A woman wanting grace may have a nimble wit, and quicke apprehenſion in earthly things, ſo that ſhee may bee able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe diſcreetly on ſuch matters, but as for the beſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19368:27"/>things, ſhe muſt come far ſhort of the gracious wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, as not being able to diſcerne of heavenly things aright, <hi>or approve the things that are excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent,</hi> as the Apoſtle hath it, <hi>Philippians</hi> 1.10. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe hath but a <hi>naiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> wit, or <hi>morall</hi> at the moſt, whereas the women that hath grace hath a <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall understanding,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.11.</note> 
               <hi>given her of God,</hi> as all his children have. Hee reveales unto all ſuch that which <hi>hee hides and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceales from the wiſe and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the world.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.25.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond thing that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly commends a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<note place="margin">2. In Love.</note>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:19368:27"/>is her <hi>love.</hi> But if ſhe be without grace, her <hi>love</hi> is little better than <hi>luſt,</hi> becauſe not ſet upon the right object, not upon God, nor the things of God, but on the baſer things below, therefore is baſe in compariſon of that love of excellent things, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is exceedingly ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ſeaſoned by the ſanctified objects.</p>
            <p>Herein therefore, the gracious woman goes far beyond ſuch as want grace, becauſe her affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are right ſet,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.33.</note> 
               <hi>ſeeking firſt the kingdome of God and his righteouſneſſe,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring the <hi>Image of God</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:19368:28"/>before all outward beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, eſteeming it dung in compariſon.</p>
            <p>A third inward quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that commends man or woman is their <hi>minde and ſpirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. In ſpirit. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> doth make a great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the ſpirit of God, and the ſpirit of the world. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.12.</note> herein ſhe that hath grace and Gods feare, doth farre exceed all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as <hi>Daniel</hi> did all the <hi>Preſidents and Princes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe an excellent ſpirit was in him.</hi> So in every one truely Religious there is a more excellent ſpirit: even the <hi>ſpirit of GOD. For if any one hath not the ſpirit of</hi> CHRIST, <hi>hee is none of his, Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>ver.</hi> 9.</p>
            <p>You ſee then how
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19368:28"/>grace makes men and women excell, becauſe it makes them, though never ſo meane, of a more excellent minde and ſpirit: And the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer Heathen could ſay, <hi>Mens cujuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> is eſt quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cicere.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The mind or ſpirit of a man is the maine man, and they did not reckon of a man according to his riches or honours, or any outward ornament, but according to his minde or ſpirit. Hee that was baſe minded was counted a baſe man, though nobly borne and greatly advanced other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes with wealth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:19368:29"/>And hee that was brave ſpirited was counted a brave man, though mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſcended,
<note place="margin">Great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in regard of their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. 1. In generall. Even as a ſicke man muſt firſt bee made whole yer he can doe the deedes of a whole man, and as the blind muſt firſt have fight given him, yer he can ſee. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Tindals</hi> Parable of the wicked Mammon <hi>p.</hi> 63. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.</note> and of low eſtate in the world.</p>
            <p>Thus much for their <hi>perſons,</hi> wherein thoſe that have grace every way ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed. Now come we to conſider their <hi>actions,</hi> and we ſhall find no leſſe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference. For firſt in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, All the actions of the unregenerate are pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted with ſinne, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.18. <hi>A good tree cannot bring forth evill fruit, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can a corrupt tree bring forth good fruit.</hi> Till wee be good wee cannot doe good, as the tree muſt be
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19368:29"/>good before it can bring forth good fruit. And 'tis grace and grace only, and the feare of God that makes us good before God, All the <hi>pruning, dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, digging, dunging,</hi> in the world, will not make a ſwore Crab-tree ſtock bring forth good Apples, unleſſe it be grafted with a graft of a good tree, <hi>you cannot gather grapes of thornes nor figges of thiſtles, Matth.</hi> 7.16. So all the <hi>pruning</hi> or <hi>dreſsing</hi> of man or woman by <hi>art and edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> will not make them bring forth acceptable fruit unto God, unleſſe they bee grafted with
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19368:30"/>grace from above. Thoſe other things may make them <hi>civill and ſober, wiſe and well reputed</hi> of in the world, but they cannot make them <hi>holy,</hi> and <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> in Gods ſight.</p>
            <p>And their beſt and moſt glorious workes of pietie and charity, which in ſome ſort they may, and doe performe, are but gliſtering ſinnes. <hi>Splendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da peccata,</hi> as Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> hath long ſince truly termed them. For ſuch offer to <hi>God</hi> a body with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſoule, becauſe grace is that which gives ſpirit, and life to all our actions, without which all we doe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19368:30"/>muſt needs bee,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1. and 9.14.</note> but <hi>dead workes,</hi> as the Scripture cals them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1.</p>
            <p>Thus much for their <hi>actions in generall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, as 1 Prayer.</note> the ſame may be ſaid of <hi>particulars;</hi> we ſhall ſee the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the one above the other to be notable. As for example, firſt in <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi> Both thoſe that have grace, and they that want grace and the feare of God, may ſet upon this holy duty; but not with the ſame ſucceſſe. The Prayers of faithfull wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, as well as men <hi>pierce the clouds, and pull downe Gods bleſsings,</hi> upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and others. As we
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19368:31"/>may ſee in <hi>Hannah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.12, 13, and 15. See <hi>Geneſis</hi> 30. ver. 1. and 20.</note> who by her prayers became of barren fruitfull, and as bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſſe was then accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a great curſe, ſo fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe was eſteemed a great bleſſing.</p>
            <p>And before and above the reſt ſhe obtained a <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel,</hi> one that had the <hi>print of his mothers prayers</hi> ſet upon his <hi>Name,</hi> for <hi>Samuel</hi> ſignifies as much as one <hi>asked</hi> or <hi>begged of God.</hi> See 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.20. This <hi>Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> this <hi>ſonne of prayer,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a worthy ſervant of the Lord, a Iudge in <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.</note> and a Prophet of the <hi>Lord,</hi> to whom God revealed Himſelfe betimes. She
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19368:31"/>
               <hi>powred out her ſoule before the Lord,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.15. and hee powred downe this great bleſſing upon her, which was the joy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing of her ſelfe, and her husband, and the ſtaffe and ſtay of all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as appeares at large in the firſt booke of <hi>Samuel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And how came <hi>Solomon</hi> to be ſo famous, and to be preferred before his el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der brethren to the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> It is more then probable, that it came to paſſe by his holy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers prayers, and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and therefore ſhee cals him the ſonne of her vowes, <hi>Pov.</hi> 31.2. vowes
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19368:32"/>and prayers being ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times taken for the very ſame.</p>
            <p>Thus good women are wonderfull helpefull to their husbands by their <hi>prayers,</hi> and alſo to their children: And indeed the whole family fares the better for them. But thoſe that want grace, Gods feare, and faith, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pray ſo as to prevaile with God. They may <hi>ſay their prayers,</hi> (as we uſe to ſay) but pray proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they cannot. For <hi>how ſhall they call on him in whom they have not belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? Rom.</hi> 10.14. If we <hi>aske not in faith wee cannot
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19368:32"/>receive any thing of GOD, Iam.</hi> 1.6, 7. wee may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſomething by Gods ordinary <hi>providence,</hi> that is extended to man and beaſt, but we receive no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by our <hi>prayers,</hi> that proceed not from grace. The prayer of faith is that which heales both ſoule and body, <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.15, 16.</p>
            <p>Therefore thoſe men and women that want faith and the feare of <hi>God,</hi> their praying is meere prating or babbling, as our Saviour ſaith of the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the heathen,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.7.</note>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> meere Battologie, and bare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition of words.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:19368:33"/>
            <p>Hence when <hi>Saul</hi> (that became <hi>Paul</hi>) was newly converted, who had made havocke of the Church before, Chriſt ſignified the ſame to <hi>Ananias</hi> in theſe words. <hi>Behold hee prayeth, Acts</hi> 9.11. <hi>Saul</hi> we read, was a ſtrict Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.5. And the <hi>Phariſees uſed to pray ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the Synagogues, and in the corners of the ſtreets,</hi> juſt as the <hi>Papists</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>hypocrites, to be ſeene of men, Mat.</hi> 6.5. And for <hi>a pretenſe made long prayers, Matth.</hi> 23.14. yet behold, now <hi>hee prayeth,</hi> ſaith the Lord, hee never prayed till now, till hee was
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19368:33"/>brought home humble to Chriſt, &amp; had his heart changed by grace from heaven, Behold <hi>now hee prayeth indeed,</hi> now his prayers are to purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe as her prayers are moſt excellent that hath grace and the feare of God,
<note place="margin">2. Al other ſpeeches.</note> ſo are her other ſpeeches. A woman that hath grace ſpeakes ſo, as to <hi>minister grace unto the hearers, Epheſ.</hi> 4.29. <hi>Shee openeth her mouth with wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: and in her tongue is the law of kindneſſe, Prov.</hi> 31.26. But it is farre o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe with thoſe that want grace, they ſpeake ſo as to miniſter rather ſin
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19368:34"/>to the hearers. Witneſſe the fond, frivolous, unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voury, and malicious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of moſt women, when they meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Not a word of grace comes out of their lippes in a long ſeaſon, they ſavour no ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe,
<note place="margin">Great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in the end of their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31.</note> they differ as much in the <hi>end</hi> of their actions, gracious women ayme at Gods glory in all their actions: which is lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle regarded of thoſe that want grace, and therefore GOD regards not their actions in any meaſure, as hee doth theirs that ſeeke his honour. For <hi>thoſe that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19368:34"/>honour me I will honour, ſaith the Lord, and they that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe me ſhall be lightly eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30.</p>
            <p>Come wee a little fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and conſider theſe 2.
<note place="margin">Differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> ſorts of women in regard of ſome relations, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther adjuncts, and we ſhall finde a vaſt difference that grace makes betweene them.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">1 In their heads.</note> a godly and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious woman is <hi>a lively member of Christ,</hi> whereas without grace women are no members at all, or elſe unſound, rotten, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt members, yea in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>limbes of Satan.</hi> And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the members partake of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19368:35"/>the honour or diſhonour of the head, ſo it is here. The lively members of Chriſt participate of his honours and dignities. <hi>For in him they are more than conquerours, Rom.</hi> 8.37. <hi>And to him that overcommeth ſaith Chriſt, I will give power over Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and hee ſhall rule them with a rod of yron,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>even as I received of my Father, Revel.</hi> 2.26, 27. <hi>And hee hath made us all Kings, Revel.</hi> 1.6. See al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo,
<note place="margin">The one ſort ſhal ſit upon the bench and the other ſtand at the barre.</note> 
               <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.21. <hi>To him that overcommeth will I grant to ſit with mee in my Throne,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>This honour have all his Saints,</hi> men and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19368:35"/>women. <hi>Know ye not that the Saints ſhall judge the world,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2. whereas all others ſhall be judged by them, and ſentenced with the Devill and his Angels, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.41. The Saints ſhall ſit on the <hi>Bench,</hi> the other ſhall ſtand at the <hi>Barre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">2. In their Husband.</note> The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of a gracious wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man appeares, in her <hi>huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,</hi> for every Chriſtian ſoule is eſpouſed unto the ſonne of God, even mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched unto Chriſt. Hence the Apoſtle ſaid that hee had <hi>eſpouſed the Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans unto one husband,
<note place="margin">Virgins in a ſpirituall not Popiſh ſenſe.</note> that he might preſent them chaſt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19368:36"/>Virgins unto</hi> CHRIST, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2.</p>
            <p>And you know that the wife partakes of her husbands honours and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies. <hi>Viri radijs co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſcant mulieres,</hi> as the Lawyers ſpeake. <hi>Women ſhine with their husbands beames,</hi> as the Moone with the light of the Sunne. If he be a <hi>Lord,</hi> ſhe is a <hi>Lady;</hi> if hee bee a <hi>King,</hi> ſhee is a <hi>Queene, &amp;c.</hi> Therefore in like manner every wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that hath true grace, whereby ſhee is matched to the moſt excellent huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band muſt needs be moſt excellent; whereas thoſe that want grace, and the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19368:36"/>feare of God, are match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and lincked by ſinne unto Satan, and ſo ſhall partake of his ſhamefull miſeries, according to the ſentence, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41. <hi>Depart into everlaſting fire prepared for the Devill and his angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<note place="margin">3 In their portion.</note> 
               <hi>Portion</hi> is an adjunct that makes a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man much ſet by and ſought after. And even in this the gracious woman hath got farre the better, more than <hi>Benjamins</hi> meſſe exceeded his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns, though the other hath many thouſands. For ſhe hath <hi>God for her portion,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> had
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19368:37"/>
               <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 16.5. and others, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 73.26. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.24. And accordingly ſhe hath the moſt excellent joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>ſhe is joynt heirewith Chriſt Ieſus, Rom.</hi> 8.17. So that ſhee hath many Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, even thoſe exceeding great and precious promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. To ſuch the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>All things are yours, whether Paul or Apollo, or Cephas or the world, or life, or death, or things preſent, or things to come, all are yours</hi> (hee ſaith it twice to make us the more ſure) <hi>and yee are Chriſts, and Chriſt is Gods,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.21, 22, 23.</p>
            <p>The ſame difference is
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19368:37"/>here as was among <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> Children,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Geneſis</hi> 25.5, 6.</note> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Iſaac</hi> and the ſons of the Concubine. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham gave all that he had unto Iſaac</hi> (ſaith the text,) <hi>but unto the ſonnes of the Concubine he gave gifts, and ſent them away.</hi> Even ſo it is in this caſe: the wicked who are but ſonnes and daughters of the Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine, baſtards indeed and not legitimate Children, have onely portions, to wit, the poore things of this life, more or leſſe, which are meane pittan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, with which they are ſent packing; when as they that feare God, being law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19368:38"/>children, have the whole inheritance, for they are Children of the promiſe as <hi>Iſaac</hi> was.</p>
            <p>Laſtly,
<note place="margin">4 Appar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell.</note> 
               <hi>Apparell</hi> is an adjunct that ſets out a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and makes her ſeeme excellent. And herein the gracious woman doth far outſtrip her that wants grace, becauſe ſhe hath put off the <hi>ragges</hi> of corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the other ſtill retaines and hugges. And ſhe hath put on the <hi>armour of light, and conſequently hath put on the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, Rom.</hi> 13.12, 13, 14. which is royall apparell indeed, more rich than all the world. Such women
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19368:38"/>as have this apparell, are like the <hi>Kings daughter, Pſalm.</hi> 45. who was <hi>all glorious within, and her clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of wrought gold, ver.</hi> 13. Every gracious wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is daughter to the great King, her clothing of wrought gold, even of that gold, <hi>which was tryed by fire,</hi> which our Saviour commanded the <hi>Laodice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> to buy of him, <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.18. which can no where elſe bee had. All the Gold in Ophyr or the Indies is but droſſe to this.</p>
            <p>In a word every graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous woman is arrayed like that woman, <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.1.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19368:39"/>
               <hi>Who was clothed with the ſunne,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mal</hi> 4.2.</note> and the Moone under her feet.</hi> So ſhe that feare God is clothed with <hi>the Sunne of righteouſneſſe,</hi> and tramples all ſublunary and earthly things under her feet, as too baſe and mear to bee advanced in her judgement and affections.</p>
            <p>And if <hi>Salomon</hi> in all his glory was not clothed like one of theſe Lillyes of the field,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.2.</note> how ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing then is the glory of theſe Lillyes among thornes, that are clothed with him, who was farre greater than <hi>Salomon? Mat.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>By all this then it is as
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19368:39"/>cleare as the ſunne, that <hi>Grace and true Religion are the moſt excellent ornaments of women, and the feare of God makes the moſt excellent wives in every reſpect.</hi> Now let us ſee what uſe and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication may be made of this.</p>
            <p>It may firſt of all ſerve to condemne the corrupt judgement of the bleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eyed world, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> that is ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the judgement of God and good men. The world mainly commends outward beauty, and bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, portion, proportion and the like, in women; but as for grace, and the feare of God, Religion
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19368:40"/>and true holines, ſo much approved by God, and extolled by the Holy Ghoſt, theſe are ſcarcely named, the world lookes aſquint at them, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure them, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in women, yea they be cryed downe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned as folly and mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 7.48, 49. and 10.20.</note> What may bee the reaſon of this? but becauſe the world wants eyes to diſcerne the worth and excellencie of the beſt things; for <hi>theſe things are ſpiritually diſcerned,</hi> 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 2.14. The Kings daughter is all glorious within, the world wants the ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19368:40"/>of faith, to looke within the vaile, and to ſee things aright, and lookes thorow the falſe glaſſe of the Devill, whereby they are delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: and hence it comes to paſſe, that <hi>that which is highly eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of men is abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the ſight of God, Luk.</hi> 16.15. and on the contrarie, that which is highly eſteemed of God is abomination in the ſight of men.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> if grace and Gods feare make moſt excellent wives, then this condemnes the carnall choyce of moſt men,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19368:41"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:19368:41"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:19368:42"/>that rather match for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney or beauty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that for grace that is the only beauty, and brings the greateſt portion, yea which brings a true title to all the promiſes and kingdome of heaven it ſelfe, which are rare and rich Iewels.</p>
            <p>A man will not bee ſo mad as to buy an horſe meerely for his ſhape and colour, but he will have a ſpeciall eye to his pace and ſtrength and mettle, that hee may bee ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and yet in this maine matter of ſeeking Wives many are ſo ſenſeleſſe, as to be carryed away with
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19368:42"/>the painted ſheath, like children, more than the blade, which is eſpecially for uſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> Learne hence what you ought principally to prize in men or women; not earthly, but ſpirituall things, not beauty and bravery, and riches and the like, but true grace and Religion, godlineſſe and the feare of God, which will make both men and women far more precious than <hi>Rubyes,</hi> or the <hi>richeſt ſtones,</hi> and which make men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men as much differ from others as <hi>Starres doe in glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:19368:43"/>
            <p>When the wiſer Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then were demanded the difference betweene Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers and thoſe that were unlearned, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded the difference, as much as was betweene a man and a beaſt: and <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>that wiſdome excelleth folly as farre as light excelleth darkneſſe, Eccleſ.</hi> 2.13. But Grace makes a farre greater dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, even as much as is betweene <hi>heaven</hi> and <hi>earth,</hi> yea as betweene <hi>heaven</hi> and <hi>hell,</hi> as plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully appeares in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer proofes.</p>
            <p>Againe, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>4</label> is it ſo, that grace and Gods feare
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19368:43"/>make moſt excellent men and women? then learne we hence to become tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excellent, by labouring moſt earneſtly and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly for grace and the true feare of God. If we could as clearly ſhew you how to excell in wo ldly wealth, or ſtrength, or beautie, &amp;c. I doubt not, but wee ſhould have fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers flocke after us, as faſt as they goe to faires and skilfull Phyſitians. Why ſhould you not much more hearken unto us in that which wil make you farre more excellent, both in ſoule and body, even excellent in the eyes
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19368:44"/>of <hi>God,</hi> and amiable in the ſight of his <hi>deare Son.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Covet earneſtly</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>the beſt gifts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vide D. Sclat. in locum.</note> 
               <hi>and yet I ſhew you a more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent way,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.31. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> it is the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlative in the Originall the moſt excellent way They were ambitious and covetous of praiſe in the Church of Corinth, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee ſhewes them the onely way to bee ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and covetous without crime or ſinne, namely by <hi>coveting moſt earneſtly the beſt gifts,</hi> which hee cals <hi>the moſt excellent way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore let other be more wealthy, ſo you
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19368:44"/>be more worthy; and let others bee more eminent and glorious in the world, and things of the world, ſo you bee moſt excellent and glorious in the beſt things, in ſpirituall and heavenly gifts.</p>
            <p>But, may ſome ſay, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> if we take this courſe to bee more truly religious, and forward in grace, and the feare of God, wee ſhall not bee accounted excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent; but rather peſtilent to the places where wee live, as wee find by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, wee ſhall be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the verie troublers of the land, &amp;c.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> This need not trouble
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19368:45"/>us, ſo long as it hath been the lot of the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſervants of God. For even <hi>Elias</hi> the <hi>reſtorer</hi> of <hi>religion</hi> in Iſrael, was ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted by wicked <hi>Ahab,</hi> who ſold himſelfe to worke wickedneſſe, <hi>Art thou hee that troubleth Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael?</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.17. when it was <hi>Ahab himſelfe and his fathers houſe, that were the troublers of the land, in that they had forſaken the commandements of God, and followed Baalim,</hi> as the Prophet replyed, verſ. 18. And S. <hi>Paul</hi> a ſingular A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, that excelled all the reſt in zeale, unwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried watchfulneſſe and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19368:45"/>diligence, was not he alſo accuſed to his face, and that before the Governor <hi>Felix,</hi> for <hi>a peſtilent fellow,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Acts</hi> 24.5.</note> 
               <hi>indeed a very plague, a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of ſedition among all the Iewes thorowout the world, and a ring-leader of the ſect of the Nazarens,</hi> for even ſo they miſcalled the true Chriſtians in thoſe dayes, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.5. who ſhall never want one nickname or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to make them odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, though they bee the <hi>excellent of the earth, of whom the world is not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy.</hi> Therefore our bleſſed Saviour bids us <hi>rejoyce and be exceeding glad,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hab.</hi> 11.38.</note> when men revile us and perſecute us, and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19368:46"/>ſay all manner of evill for his names ſake falſely, becauſe even ſo perſecuted they the Prophets that were before us, and great is our reward in heaven, Matth.</hi> 5.11, 12.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtles that were the moſt <hi>excellent,</hi> yet were eſteemed <hi>as the filth of the world, and off-ſcouring of all things,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13. The excellency of thoſe that have true grace is out of the reach of humane reaſon, and this makes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deſpiſe that which they cannot diſcerne. And who would not rather bee excellent, and yet eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vile, as Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his Apoſtles
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19368:46"/>were, than being baſe and vile, by reaſon of ſinne, to bee highly eſteemed and extolled in the world?</p>
            <p>Wherefore I ſay again, <hi>covet earneſtly theſe beſt gifts,</hi> to wit, of grace and the true feare of GOD, <hi>which is the moſt excellent way,</hi> notwithſtanding all the ignominie &amp; reproch, all the deriſion and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, that the wicked world can caſt upon it. And know this withall, that nothing is <hi>excellent,</hi> but it is alſo <hi>difficult.</hi> You muſt not looke to excell, and yet live as you liſt, as the moſt, eſpecially great men and women uſe to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19368:47"/>doe. <hi>The kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> (which is the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent kingdom) <hi>ſuffereth violence</hi> (ſaith our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our) <hi>and the violent take it by force, Mat.</hi> 11.12. You muſt therefore be <hi>violent</hi> for grace and Gods king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, if you meane to be excellent.</p>
            <p>See therefore that with diligence you ſet upon the moſt excellent and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult duties, as <hi>ſelfe-denyall,</hi> ſerious <hi>examination</hi> of your owne hearts and wayes, <hi>frequent praying, reading, hearing, and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating</hi> in the good word of <hi>God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 20.32.</note> the word of his grace, <hi>Conferring and keeping com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19368:47"/>with ſuch</hi> eſpecially as feare the Lord, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 119.63. and excell in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 16.3.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5.15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>Walking circumſpectly, or exactly, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming the time becauſe the dayes are evill; perfecting holineſſe in the feare of God,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. <hi>For God hath commanded to keepe his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts diligently, or very much Pſal.</hi> 119.4. <hi>And curſed is the deceiver, that in his flocke hath a male, and ſacrificeth unto the LORD a corrupt thing, for I am a great King ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, and my name is dreadfull among the heathen, Mal.</hi> 1.14.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>5</label> let not any think that theſe things will not
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19368:48"/>ſtand with their ſtate, and place or birth and the like. For this in the Text was ſpoken by a <hi>worthy Queene</hi> written by a <hi>famous King,</hi> to wit, wiſe <hi>Solomon,</hi> and that concerning the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations of <hi>a great wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man eſpecially,</hi> as interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters obſerve, And owned by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> for part of Gods <hi>pure word, given by inſpiration from GOD.</hi> Yea let them know, that Grace and true Religion ſincerely followed, is the Crowne of greatneſſe, and the faireſt flower in their garden, or Garland that ſit upon the higheſt thrones. As it was farre
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19368:48"/>greater honour for <hi>David</hi> to bee ſtiled a man after Gods owne heart for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, and zeale, than when the women ſang <hi>Saul</hi> hath ſlaine his thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, and <hi>David</hi> his tenne thouſand, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.7.</p>
            <p>And ſo I come in a word to the laſt words of my Text. <hi>But a woman that feareth the Lord ſhee ſhall bee praiſed.</hi> Hence we may obſerve. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>It is our bounden duty to praiſe thoſe that be praiſe-worthy, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſuch as excell in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reaſon is ready, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> that others may be incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to labour for the like
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19368:49"/>notable and eminent ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and graces. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> As alſo to confirme ſuch as take the ſame courſes, that they may never bee weary of well doing, nor faint in the wayes of grace and godlineſſe, wherein they ſhall be ſure to meete with diſcouragements more than a few in this preſent evill world. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> It may ſerve alſo to quicken others in the wayes of Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, praiſe being a ſpeciall ſpurre to that purpoſe, as we finde by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience. And ſo I come briefely to the applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the point.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> If praiſe bee ſuch a due
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19368:49"/>debt to thoſe that doe vertuouſly, and eſpecially to them that excell in grace, and in the feare of God, then let none bee ſo croſſe and oppoſite unto God as to condemne thoſe, whom the Lord commends, let none be ſo baſe minded as to cry out upon ſuch as follow faſteſt after grace and true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. For <hi>he that juſtifieth the wicked, and he that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth the juſt, even they both are an abomination to the Lord, Pro.</hi> 17 15.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> Let none be offended to heare the due and deſerved praiſes of thoſe that excell in grace
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19368:50"/>and Gods holy feare. For ſome are more deſirous to have wicked men and women flattered, and ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in their ſinfull, and graceleſſe courſes, than to heare the praiſes of ſuch as bee holy and heavenly minded, becauſe they are like to the former, and moſt unwilling to tread in ſtraight ſteps of the latter. But <hi>woe be to them that call evill good, and good evill, Iſa.</hi> 5.20. <hi>He that</hi> thus <hi>bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his friend, riſing early in the morning, it ſhall be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a curſe to him, Pro.</hi> 27.14. To bleſſe and praiſe men or women without deſert, is no bleſſing, but a
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19368:50"/>curſe, and on the contrary, to bleſſe and praiſe where there is juſt ground, will be a means to bring a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. And thus much ſhall ſuffice for the Text. Now may wee ſeaſonably pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the occaſion.</p>
            <p>Concerning this moſt worthy Gentlewoman,
<note place="margin">The occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> for whoſe ſake we are here aſſembled; I may ſafely ſay without ſtrayning, as my Text leades me, <hi>Many daughters have done vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, but thou excelleſt them all.</hi> I ſpeake it without diſpraiſe to any, take her every way, and ſhe goes beyond all, that ever I knew, in my apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19368:51"/>and that eſpecially in theſe three reſpects. 1. If you conſider her age, 2. The time of her ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and 3. Her ranke and parentage.</p>
            <p>For her <hi>age,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <note place="margin">For her age.</note> She was but full three and twentie the laſt month, and yet ſo growne in grace, that ſhee might ſeeme rather three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore and three, for gravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſobriety and modeſty, matching the eldeſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons. She had but a ſhort time to runne her race, and God gave her an heart to make haſte, for ſhe ranne ſo faſt, that ſhee not only <hi>overtooke,</hi> but <hi>over-ranne</hi> all her fellowes.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:19368:51"/>
            <p>For her <hi>time of ſtanding,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> it was about 7. yeares,
<note place="margin">Her time of ſtanding</note> ſhe ſerved an Apprentiſhip, and was therein ſo true to her heavenly maker, that he thought her fully fit to be made free, not only in the kingdom of grace but of glory. She was ſo good a ſcholar in CHRISTS Schoole, that ſhe was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to take her higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, to wit, in heaven, long before the uſuall time, as ſome doe in the Vniverſity <hi>propter excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentiam,</hi> for their excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie above their fellowes. For in ſeaven yeares ſhee learned more, than many, (and thoſe true Chriſtians
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19368:52"/>too) in 7. times 7. yeares.</p>
            <p>And for her <hi>rancke and parentage,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <note place="margin">Her rancke and paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</note> She was deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of no meane family, ſhee came of ſome very <hi>honourable anceſtours,</hi> yet ſo humble, and lowly was ſhe, and denyed her ſelfe ſo much for her Saviours ſake, that ſhe would be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar with the meaneſt that made conſcience of their wayes, and had the feare of God before their eyes, preferring ſuch as were rich in faith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.5.</note> far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any other, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo gay, and glorious in the world.</p>
            <p>Yea in all theſe three reſpects ſhe was one of a
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:19368:52"/>thouſand, nay one of ten thouſand, and therfore the fitter to be fully matched with him, <hi>that is chiefeſt of ten thouſand, Cant.</hi> 5.10. So that I may very well apply all thoſe former excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies unto her, wherein women truely fearing <hi>God</hi> farre exceed all other wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <p>And firſt for <hi>Birth,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> hers was of the beſt,
<note place="margin">Her birth of the beſt.</note> ſhee was moſt nobly borne moſt royally deſcended, being partaker of the new birth, borne from above, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of God, who <hi>of his owne will begat her by the word of truth, Iam.</hi> 1.18. which ſhe moſt evidently
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:19368:53"/>expreſſed, by that great <hi>reſpect and reverence</hi> which ſhe ever after bare to that <hi>bleſſed inſtrument of her hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly birth, Gods holy word,</hi> making it her <hi>delight and counſellour,</hi> as the Prophet did, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.24.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> As ſhee had the beſt <hi>birth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Her beauty</note> ſo ſhe obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the moſt excellent <hi>beauty,</hi> even the beauty of holines, the bleſſed image of God, which made her moſt amiable in the eyes of all thoſe that were well acquainted with her, and could diſcerne the things that be excellent, and even dazled the eyes of others. So beautifull was ſhee in
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19368:53"/>this beſt kinde, that ſhee did much grace and adorn the Goſpell, and beautifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her profeſſion, whereas ſome are a blot and ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh unto it.</p>
            <p>And therefore in the third place ſhe muſt needs be well favoured, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <note place="margin">Her favour</note> for her parts were well proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. She was a true <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth, walking in all the Commandements and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of the Lord blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe,</hi> like that <hi>Elizabeth, Luk.</hi> 1.6. And was not like thoſe women that have many good parts, but withall ſome ſuch <hi>foule in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities,</hi> that they ſtaine and ſpoyle all that is good
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:19368:54"/>in them, ſo that they cauſe the name of God, and his word to be <hi>blaſphemed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> For her un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding:
<note place="margin">Her un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</note> ſhe was able to diſcerne thoſe myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries which are hid from the wiſe and prudent, for ſhe perceived an excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in things above, which made her ſo ready <hi>to runne the wayes of Gods Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements,</hi> when others ſcarce goe in them. Shee was able by an heavenly inſtinct, to <hi>distinguiſh the voyce of Chriſt from the voyce of a ſtranger,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.4, 5.</note> which made her <hi>eſteeme all other things dung in compariſon of the excellency of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:19368:54"/>of Chriſt Ieſus, Philip.</hi> 3.8.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, For her <hi>Love,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
               <note place="margin">Her Love.</note> it was truly excellent and of the beſt ſtamp, for it was ſet upon the right ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, upon God and the things of God, in the firſt place, ſo that ſhee could ſay with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>whom have I in heaven but thee, and I deſire none in earth beſides thee, Pſal.</hi> 73.25. And with the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs. <hi>None but Chriſt,
<note place="margin">S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn Lambert. Mart.</hi>
                  </note> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Her <hi>charity</hi> alſo was to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all, even her utter enemies, for ſhe could doe good againſt evill, but her ſpeciall love was to the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:19368:55"/>Saints, in whom was her delight. She well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood and made much uſe of that Article of the Creed, which few con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, <hi>(The Communion of Saints)</hi> being very open-hearted and open-handed to ſuch as ſhe thought true members of that bleſſed ſociety. And if ſhe ſeemed ſparing at any time, it was to ſpend the more liberal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the lively mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt, in which regard ſhee did match the <hi>Macedonians,</hi> whoſe grace Saint <hi>Paul</hi> much commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, becauſe <hi>to their power (he bare record) yea and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond their power, they were
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:19368:55"/>willing of themſelves.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Herein where moſt Chriſtians come ſhort ſhe excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Their love is leſs than their meanes, hers above her abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note> And ſo was ſhe, as many can beare record, and this becauſe ſhe had <hi>firſt given her ſelfe to the Lord, and then to others by the will of God, as they did,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</p>
            <p>In a word her love to her deare and familiar friends was like the love of <hi>Ionathan</hi> unto <hi>David, wonderfull, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the love of women,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.26. She was indeed a true <hi>Ionathan</hi> being <hi>Iah-nathan</hi> a ſpeciall gift of God.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/>
               <note place="margin">Her ſpirit. <hi>Ruach jat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tira, Dan.</hi> 6. and 3.</note> for <hi>Her ſpirit</hi> ſhe might well bee called the <hi>Daughter</hi> of <hi>Daniel,</hi> becauſe <hi>Ruach Iattira</hi> as the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dee hath it, <hi>an excellent ſpirit was in her:</hi> Though the weaker veſſell, yet had ſhe a
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:19368:56"/>maſculine, heroicke, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible ſpirit, to reſiſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan and his inſtruments, whenſoever ſhee was ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be hindred from <hi>Gods</hi> ſervice. O how couragiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly would ſhe break through all impediments, that might any way hinder her from holy duties, even as <hi>Samſon ſnapt aſunder the cords and withes! Iudg.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>With what an holy indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation did ſhee skorne the wealth and pleaſures of this preſent world, as droſſe and ſcum in compariſon of the true treaſure! And how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted in defending the truth and thoſe that ſtood for the ſame! She was not aſhamed of Chriſtian any
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:19368:56"/>company, as many coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Chriſtians are.</p>
            <p>Thus much for thoſe things that were applyed to the perſon of woman in the proofe of the point.
<note place="margin">Next for her Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, firſt in generall.</note> Now come wee to her actions, which were like her ſelfe, ſanctified and ſingular. For <hi>Religion was her maſter-piece,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.12.</note> as this worthy womans in the text, ſhee was one that <hi>feared God from her youth</hi> and therefore her actions pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from a right roote, and clear ſpring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he was no hipocrite, I dare boldly ſay, for ſhee was not ſo much in <hi>ſhew</hi> as in <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> not more in <hi>words</hi> than in <hi>deeds</hi> but as <hi>God</hi> had given he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 2. <hi>hands</hi> to one <hi>tongue,</hi> ſo her deeds
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:19368:57"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:19368:57"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:19368:58"/>doubled her words, and though thus double handed in all her doings, contrary to the courſe of the world yet moſt ſingle hearted.</p>
            <p>In particular for her pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <note place="margin">In particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar for her prayers. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 12.3, 4.</note> they were not cold, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zie, and lukewarm, but ſuch as pierced the skies, like thoſe of <hi>Cornelius, Act.</hi> 10.4. O how would ſhee wraſtle with God in prayer! how would ſhe flye to the throne of grace as it were upon the wings of faith! And how often hath ſhe bin obſerved to riſe from prayer, with teares in her eyes, on her cheekes, and dropped down before her! and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any oſtentation, which ſhe was as free from, as any
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:19368:58"/>that ever I obſerved. I ſpeake by experience.</p>
            <p>As much may be ſaid for her <hi>diligent and dutifull hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> (to adde an inſtance or two more.)
<note place="margin">And hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Gods Word.</note> For ſhe delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not in houſes of <hi>play, and pleaſure,</hi> as moſt young Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen doe, but the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of <hi>praying and preaching were her chiefe joy.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 137.5, 6.</note> So that whatſoever paines ſhee was able to take ſhe was willing to undergoe, to come to thoſe places where ſhee might heare God moſt live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpeaking unto her, and ſhe againe moſt powerfully like <hi>Hannah, powre out her ſoule unto the Lord.</hi> Mourning for nothing more in time of her ſickneſſe, than the want of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:19368:59"/>
               <hi>Gods</hi> houſe and ordinances, for nothing but Neceſſitie could keepe her from them, which is far otherwiſe, with a great many eſpecially of her ranck, who are but too eaſily intreated to keep from the Church, even when <hi>God</hi> himſelfe, their own, and the Churches neceſſities call upon them.</p>
            <p>And while ſhee was hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, how marvellous atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive! even as was ſaid of the people, that heard our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.48. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>they were attentive to him, or rather hanged upon him as the</hi> margent hath it in the laſt tranſlation; So ſhe han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged upon the mouth of his meſſengers, as Chickens
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:19368:59"/>hang upon the mouth of the Hen, (as ſome open the phraſe) that are ready to catch whatſoever ſhee ſhall breake for them, or let fall unto them.</p>
            <p>Even ſo her <hi>comming to the Sacrament was admirable.</hi>
               <note place="margin">And recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</note> How ſolemne and ſerious would ſhee be in preparing for that holy <hi>Supper,</hi> ſetting apart ſometimes <hi>dayes of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and humiliation</hi> (which were dayes of <hi>Iubilee</hi> to her ſanctified ſpirit) that ſhee might come the more hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry and thirſty, and ſo bee more fully ſatisfied with the <hi>fat and ſweet</hi> of this moſt <hi>heavenly Table.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seldome did ſhee receive this bleſſe. Sacrament with
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:19368:60"/>dry eyes, as I have bin often an eye witneſſe (though ſhe carryed it covertly, and yet how often did ſhe frequent this holy Feaſt! never miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the monthly Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, if ſhee were able to come to the Church, and that I think for 7. yeares to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, after once it had pleaſed the Lord to let the light of his countenance ſhine upon her, wherein ſhe followed a good patterne given her at home.</p>
            <p>Theſe are ſtrange things, you will think, but I can aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you, <hi>not ſo ſtrange as true,</hi> for I do not ſpeak, as we muſt do many times by hear-ſay, but I ſpeak, what I have ſeen and knowne.</p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:19368:60"/>
            <p>And now for her words and ſpeeches ſhe had learn'd <hi>the language of Canaan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Her words. <hi>Jſa.</hi> 19.8. <hi>Neh.</hi> 13.24.</note> and did not mingle it with the <hi>ſpeech of Aſhdod,</hi> ſhe was not double-tongued but ſpake the words <hi>of ſoberneſſe and truth.</hi> She loved <hi>that pure language, Zeph.</hi> 3.9. and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted lying, and ſwearing, yea ſhe abhorred all <hi>rotten ſpeech and corrupt communication,</hi> as filthy vomit, labouring to have <hi>her ſpeeches alwaies with grace,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 4.6.</note> ſeaſoned with ſalt</hi> as the Apoſtle commandes.</p>
            <p>And for the <hi>end</hi> of her Actions,
<note place="margin">The end of her actions</note> She exceedingly aymed at Gods glory, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring that before all, ſo that ſhe would often ſay. <hi>If ſhe could but glorifie God ſhee
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:19368:61"/>cared not.</hi> For ſhe had learnt by heart that hard leſſon of <hi>Selfe deny all</hi> for Gods ſake.</p>
            <p>Now in the laſt place to come to thoſe relations, and adjuncts of excellency.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> She was a moſt live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly member of Chriſts my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall body,
<note place="margin">Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in her <hi>Head.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. She had conqueſt upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, one victory af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ano<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther.</note> and therefore moſt honourable in Her head. Witneſſe thoſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy workes before related. She was <hi>in Chriſt her head more than a Conquerour, Rom.</hi> 8.37. ſhe did <hi>over-overcome,</hi> as one well renders the words. For ſhe conquered the corruptions of youth, of her place, of the times and places wherein ſhe lived, and therefore now no doubt is gone to weare the crown of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:19368:61"/>righteouſnes, having <hi>fought ſo good a fight of faith,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7, 8.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> She was no leſſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in her <hi>Husband</hi> than in her <hi>head,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</note> which are the ſame, for ſhe was eſpouſed unto Chriſt, her heavenly husband, with whoſe beams of grace ſhe did ſhine bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie while ſhe was here, and therefore now ſhe gliſters gloriouſly as the Sun, with his moſt orient beames of bliſſe and happineſſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. For her Portion, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> that was <hi>no corruptible thing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In her Portion.</note> 
               <hi>as ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver or gold,</hi> but even the <hi>Lord</hi> of heaven, whoſe mercy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures for ever, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of whom ſhee eſteemed al earthly treaſure but droſſe
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:19368:62"/>and dunge. And therefore now ſhe is gone to take poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of that goodly joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the kingdom of glory, being joynt-heire with <hi>Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17.</note> For on earth women doe not enjoy their joynture, but the time of life after their Husbands death, but 'tis otherwiſe in heaven, for they go to take a fuller poſſeſſion of their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall joynture by death, which is the dore of eternall life to them <hi>that die in the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> for her Apparell, it was of the choyceſt and beſt,
<note place="margin">In her Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell.</note> even the Royal Robes of Chriſts righteouſnes, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ſhe had put on by faith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3 9.</note> 
               <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing her own righteouſnes,</hi>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:19368:62"/>as rotten ragges in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, often complaining of her owne unrighteouſneſſe. And yet wheras other Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen are much taken up with providing for the body, tricking and trimming that painted ſheath, for it is no better oftentimes,
<note place="margin">See <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.15. in the Chaldee. <hi>Vestite vos ſerico pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitatis. byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſino ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis purpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra pudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia. Taliter pigmentatae Deum habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitu ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torem,</hi> Ter. <hi>de cul. foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minarum.</hi>
               </note> ſhee mainely minded the trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and decking of her ſoule, by her daily devotion, wherein ſhe excelled, hating the fond and flaring, phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſticall and new fangled fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions of the world, as fit for none but idle braines, vaine and wanton women, that want eyes to look into their precious ſoule, and ſee how needy and naked, tattered &amp; deformed they are within.</p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:19368:63"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:19368:63"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:19368:64"/>
            <p>Shee therefore now (no doubt) is arrayed like thoſe in the Revelation, <hi>that had long white Robes, and Palmes in their hands, in ſigne of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, Rev.</hi> 7.9. <hi>For ſhe came out of great tribulation, and had waſhed her Robe, and made it white in the bloud of the Lamb</hi> v.
<note place="margin">Ver. 16.17.</note> 14. <hi>So that now ſhee ſhall hunger no more, nor thirſt any more, all teares being wiped from her eyes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 57.1, 2.</note> though not from ours. For wee have great cauſe to weepe and mourne, not for her, but for our ſelves. The greater her gaine is, the greater is our loſſe, and not ours only, but the whole Church of God.</p>
            <p>Thus much for her <hi>life.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Of Her death.</note> Now concerning her <hi>death,</hi>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:19368:64"/>I muſt ſay ſomething, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe gave me as it were a charge, intreating me to ſpeake that which I ſhall briefly declare unto you.</p>
            <p>The firſt day that ſhe fell ill, I went unexpectedly to ſee her, wherin ſhe acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged Gods ſpeciall provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. I found her indeed ſomthing ſad, yea more than ordinary, not for feare of Death, but becauſe that her diſeaſe was likely to be ſuch as would deprive her of her friends, hence thoſe teares.
<note place="margin">To wit, the ſmall Poxe</note> I told her ſhee was in the hands of a wiſe and tender Father, who knew beſt what was fit for us, and therefore ſhee needed not ſo much to be troubled at that. After we
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:19368:65"/>had commended her caſe unto God in Prayer,
<note place="margin">She deſired to be bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the diſeaſe.</note> ſhe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated me that after her bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryall (for ſhe made full ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to die) I would make a Sermon, and therein per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the hearers to theſe two things.</p>
            <p>The firſt was,
<note place="margin">Her firſt deſire.</note> 
               <hi>that you would hearken to the Word of God better than ſhe had done.</hi> To which I preſently reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (as well as I could for teares being much affected with her words) I would they would heare but ſo well as ſhe did. Yet, belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, my deſire is as hers was, that you would hearken better then ſhe did, which if I could perſwade you all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, I ſhould thinke my ſelfe
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:19368:65"/>the happieſt man in the world. For herein ſhe did excell, as I ſaid before, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever in her humility and zeale to Gods word ſhe thus ſpake.</p>
            <p>Therefore let me intreat you to grant this her holy deſire. If it bee poſſble, <hi>hearken to Gods holy Word bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than ſhee did.</hi> But if this be impoſſble, as almoſt it is, yet hearken ſo as ſhee did, and you ſhall undoubtedly be bleſſed. For as ſhe had a very good memory, for good things eſpecially, ſo had ſhe a moſt artentive eare and heart, even like <hi>Mary that choſe that good, part which ſhould not bee taken from her, Luk.</hi> 10.42. And like thoſe
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:19368:66"/>
               <hi>Noble Bereans, Acts</hi> 17.11, 12. <hi>Who were ſaid to bee</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>more generous than thoſe of Theſſalonica, firſt in that they received the Word with all readineſſe of mind, and ſecondly, in that they ſearched the Scriptures daily, whether thoſe things were ſo, therefore many of them beleeved; alſo of honourable women, and of men not a few.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea ſo hungry was ſhe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Gods holy Word, that <hi>ſhee feared no famine,</hi> but that threatned by the Prophet <hi>Amos. Not a famine of bread, but of hearing the Word of the Lord, Amos</hi> 8.11. Oh therefore that you could but equall, if not exceed her in this! Then might
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:19368:66"/>you find that moſt raviſhing comfort in hearing,
<note place="margin">The laſt Lords day ſave one as ſhe told us at that time. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</note> which ſhe confeſſed ſhe found a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before ſhe fell ſicke.</p>
            <p>The other thing ſhe deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be commended unto you was this. <hi>That you would have a ſpeciall care to looke to your Families,</hi> She meant in regard of religious orders, which are ſo much neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in moſt places, men li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving athome more like hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens and Infidels than true Chriſtians. For though ſhe did more than moſt in this kind, yet was it a great griefe unto her, that ſhe could not doe better. Oh that you would let her have her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire in this alſo! you would find the bleſſing above mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:19368:67"/>if you did but once ſet up <hi>the power of godlineſſe in your families,</hi> that you might be ſaid <hi>to feare God, with all your houſe as Cornelius</hi> did, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.2. For by this meanes this good Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman was truly ſaid to be a prop, or pillar in the houſe.</p>
            <p>So that her Husband, and Children, (if they were of yeares) might joyne in her praiſes, as they before the Text. <hi>Her Children might ariſe and call her bleſſed,
<note place="margin">Some re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre theſe words of the Text to the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</note> her Husband alſo might praiſe her, ſaying; Many daughters have done vertuouſly, or valiantly; but thou excelleſt, and goeſt above them all,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Indeed <hi>her wayes ſo pleaſed</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 16.7.</note>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:19368:67"/>
               <hi>the Lord, that her enemies were at peace with her,</hi> as <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſaith, And what I ſpeake a cloud of witneſſes will teſtifie. Therefore I need the leſſe feare to bee accuſed either of <hi>Falſe hood or Flattery,</hi> which I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes abhorred in every place, eſpecially in the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, and ſo did ſhe, which made her ſomtime ſay, that ſhee would deſire nothing might be ſaid of her at her death, becauſe ſhe had with ſorrow heard, ſome <hi>ſainted</hi> at their death, who were lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle better than <hi>devils</hi> in their life.</p>
            <p>Let none therefore take that with the left hand which I have reached out
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:19368:68"/>with the right, as <hi>Saul</hi> did the due and deſerved com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations given to <hi>David,</hi> For <hi>I ſpeak that truth in Chriſt, I lie not, my conſcience alſo bearing me witneſſe, Rom.</hi> 9.1.</p>
            <p>Nay, if I ſhould reckon all the rarities of this right religious Gentlewoman, that I have beene an eye, and eare-witneſſe of, from her firſt to her laſt, <hi>Dies me deſiceret,</hi> The day would faile me, my ſpirits would bee ſpent, and I ſhould tire your patience, and it might make moſt of us bluſh and be aſhamed to ſee how farre we come ſhort, and all of us admire and ſtand amazed, and aſtoniſhed at the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and grace of GOD ſo
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:19368:68"/>plentifully powred upon her.</p>
            <p>Therefore to conclude, Happy was (yea, and ſtill is) the <hi>Mother</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> Happy the Husband in ſuch a <hi>Wife,</hi> and happy <hi>chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Mother,</hi> who hath laid up many <hi>prayers,</hi> better than <hi>portions</hi> for them. And happie were all her <hi>acquaintance</hi> in ſuch a <hi>friend,</hi> And yet more hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie they and wee in follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her heavenly ſteps. But moſt happy ſhe, that led ſo holy and heavenly a life. Becauſe <hi>bleſſed are the dead which die in the Lord, even ſo ſaith the ſpirit, that they may reſt from their labors, and their works follow them, Rev.</hi> 14 13.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:19368:69"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Weekes.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19368:69"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
